Ismini Lourentzou | CV

🛘 (217) 419 6979 🔹 🖂 lourent2@illinois.edu 🔹 🚱 isminoula.github.io

My research interests lie in the intersection of Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing and Information Retrieval. My work is tackling all sorts of bottlenecks related to data noise, sparsity, domain shift and lack of annotations. I mainly focus on **Active and Semi-supervised learning** and lately on **Domain Adaptation**. Another big part of my work is **Deep Learning for Social Media Analysis**. I have also worked on interdisciplinary projects that touch societal problems. Excited about work in areas such as Reinforcement Learning, Game Theory and Meta-learning.

Education

University of Illinois at Urbana - Champaign

PhD Computer Science , Advisor: Prof. ChengXiang Zhai

Athens University of Economics and Business, Athens, Greece

B.S. Computer Science, July 2013, Advisor: Prof. Michalis Vazirgiannis
 Thesis Topic: Automated Snippet Generation for Online Advertising

Athens University of Economics and Business, Athens, Greece

 B.S. Business Administration, October 2009, Advisor: Prof. Vassilis Orfanos Thesis Topic: The Implications of Basel II on the Greek Banking Sector

Awards

- o Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award CS Department @ UIUC, Fall 2017
- o Travel Award for ISWC 2018, Pacific Grove, CA (declined)
- o Travel Award for ISWC 2017, Vienna, Austria
- o Travel Award for IEEE Big Data 2017, Boston, MA
- Travel Award for WiML 2017 (co-located with NIPS'17), Long Beach, CA
- Microsoft Azure Research Award (November 2014)
 - 14 awards given by Microsoft: access to Azure for research purposes (estimated value: \$20,000)

Proposal: Multivariate Time Series Analysis for Trend Forecasting

- o Yahoo! Certificate of Achievement for the most useful and cool project
 - CS 511 Advanced Data Management course, Spring 2014, Instructor: Prof. Kevin Chang

Project: "Multi-resolution drill-down with clustering and sampling"

- Selected from the University of Illinois at Urbana at Champaign, Computer Science Department
 as one of the three nominees for the Microsoft Graduate Women's Scholarship for 2014
- o IPL at ImageClef 2013 AMIA Medical Task: 2^{nd} place in Textual and 5^{th} place in Visual Ad-hoc image-based retrieval

Publications

- [1] Lourentzou, Ismini, Anna Lisa Gentile, Daniel Gruhl, Jane Fortner, Michele Freemon, and Kendra Grande. Difficult relations: Extracting novel facts from text. In *International Semantic Web Conference*. Springer, 2018.
- [2] Chase Geigle, Lourentzou, Ismini, Hari Sundaram, and ChengXiang Zhai. Clads: a cloud-based virtual lab for the delivery of scalable hands-on assignments for practical data science education. In Proceedings of the 23rd Annual ACM Conference on Innovation and Technology in Computer Science Education. ACM, 2018.
- [3] Lourentzou, Ismini, Alfredo Alba, Anni Coden, Anna Lisa Gentile, Daniel Gruhl, and Steve Welch. Mining relations from unstructured content. In *Pacific-Asia Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining*. Springer, 2018.
- [4] **Lourentzou, Ismini**, Daniel Gruhl, and Steve Welch. Exploring the efficiency of batch active learning for human-in-the-loop relation extraction. In *Companion of The Web Conference 2018*, 2018.
- [5] Lourentzou, Ismini, Alex Morales, and ChengXiang Zhai. Text-based geolocation prediction of social media users with neural networks. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017.

- [6] Sophie Lohmann, Lourentzou, Ismini, Chengxiang Zhai, and Dolores Albarracín. Who is saying what on twitter: An analysis of messages with references to hiv and hiv risk behavior. In Acta de investigacion psicologica, 2018.
- [7] Ruby Mendenhall, Nicole Brown, Michael L Black, Mark Van Moer, Lourentzou, Ismini, Karen Flynn, Malaika Mckee, and Assata Zerai. Rescuing lost history: Using big data to recover black women's lived experiences. In Proceedings of the XSEDE16 Conference on Diversity, Big Data, and Science at Scale, 2016.
- [8] Lourentzou, Ismini, Graham Dyer, Abhishek Sharma, and ChengXiang Zhai. Hotspots of news articles: Joint mining of news text & social media to discover controversial points in news. In 2015 IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.
- [9] Stamatina Thomaidou, Lourentzou, Ismini, Panagiotis Katsivelis-Perakis, and Michalis Vazirgiannis. Automated snippet generation for online advertising. In Proceedings of the 22nd ACM international conference on Conference on information & knowledge management. ACM, 2013.
- [10] Spyridon Stathopoulos, Lourentzou, Ismini, Antonia Kyriakopoulou, and Theodore Kalamboukis. Ipl at clef 2013 medical retrieval task. In CLEF 2013 Online Working Notes, 2013.

Research Experience

HIV Radar project

UIUC

Research Assistant

Fall 2015, Spring 2016

Interdisciplinary research, PI: Prof. Dolores Albarracin

Analyzing social and online media influences on HIV/STI transmission behaviors

from Twitter and sociodemographic variables. More information on the project website:

https://www.socialactionlab.org/hsmg

Big Data methods for social sciences

UIUC

Fall 2014 - Spring 2016

February 2013 - June 2013

{Spring, Summer, Fall} 2014, Spring 2015

Research Assistant Interdisciplinary research, PI: Prof. Ruby Mendenhall

Analyzing big-data collections with missing metadata to recover books and articles

related to black women's lived experiences. PI received an HPC Innovation Excellence

Award for this project

iTextNetMiner - Topic Summarization & opinion integration

UIUC

Research Assistant

PI: Kaizhi Tang, Intelligent Automation Inc A Scalable, Distributed and Modular Toolkit for Mining Text-Rich Heterogeneous

Information Networks to Enhance Contextual Understanding: iTextNetMiner

Information Retrieval Group at ImageClef 2013 - AMIA: Medical Task

AUEB

Research Assistant

Supervisor: Prof. Theodore Kalamboukis

Developped the Textual Ad-hoc image-based retrieval method that was placed second in the ImageClef'13 competition

Ad Creative Generation (Bachelor Thesis Project)

AUEB

Research Assistant

Supervisor: Prof. Michalis Varzigiannis

Implemented the Information Extraction and the Sentiment Analysis phases

Text generation system that, given a product landing page as input, can produce

short advertising text (snippets) in an automated and massive manner

Teaching Experience

CS410DSO - Text Information Systems

Teaching Assistant @UIUC

Fall 2018, 2017, 2016

July 2012 - June 2013

Instructor: Prof. ChengXiang Zhai

Graduate level course in Text Informatics offered online for the MCS-DS degree

CS410 - Text Information Systems

Teaching Assistant @UIUC

Spring, 2017

Instructor: Prof. ChengXiang Zhai Graduate level course in Text Informatics

CS125 - Introduction to Computer Science

Teaching Assistant @UIUC
Instructor: Prof. Craig Zilles

Introductory course in computing for CS majors

Work Experience

IBM Research - Intelligence Augmentation Team

Research Intern Summer 2018, 2017

Mentor: Dr. Daniel Gruhl

Summer 2018: Combining Active with Semi-supervised learning.

Summer 2017: Active learning for real-time domain-specific relation extraction.

Microsoft Research - Machine Teaching group

[°] Research Intern Summer 2015

Mentor: Dr. Patrice Simard

Exploring dictionary refinement and active learning. Dictionaries are leveraged in the ICE platform to bridge the gap between non-machine learning experts and the document classification system.

Packt Publishing

O Technical Reviewer April - June 2014, Aug. - Sept. 2013

D3 for Dynamic Data Visualizations video courses, Alexander Simoes

Data Visualization with D3.js Cookbook, Nick Qi Zhu, ISBN: 9781782162162

National Bank of Greece S.A.

, Business Loans, Imports - Exports & Foreign Exchange

October 2005 - August 2013

National Bank of Greece S.A., Shipping Branch

Customers of this particular branch are only shipping companies, both foreign & local. February 2004 - October 2005

Other Activities

PURE - Promoting Undergraduate Research in Engineering

Mentor for CS undergraduate students
12-week research mentorship program

Fall 2014 - Spring 2015

CS Graduate Ambassador

Welcoming prospective graduate students

Spring 2014, 2015, 2016, 2017

Technical and Personal skills

- Programming Languages and Tools: Python, D3.js, Java, Matlab/Scilab/Octave/R, C#/C++, SQL/mySQL, UNIX Shell Scripting, LaTeX, HTML, CSS, Awk, F#
- o Deep Learning packages: pyTorch, keras, openNMT, torchtext

Online courses

Statements of Accomplishment from Coursera in:

Machine Learning, Prof. Andrew Ng - Stanford University

Computing for Data Analysis, Prof. Roger D. Peng - Johns Hopkins University

NLP, Prof. D. Jurafsky & Prof. Ch. Manning - Stanford University

Languages

Greek: Native

English: Fluent (Certificate of Proficiency in English, University of Michigan - 2002)

French: Beginners (Delf - Level I - 2002)

Fall, 2013